Finding Aid for Samuel D. Pepper Papers 1893-1952
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Samuel D. Pepper Papers 1893-1952
Pepper, Samuel Dewitt, 1877-1960.
Port Huron, Michigan attorney; officer in the Michigan National Guard beginning in 1905, later Judge Advocate with the U.S. Army during World War I. After the war, Pepper was chief law officer of the MNG where he was advisor during the Flint Sit-Down strike of 1937. Biographical material; correspondence with family and friends concerning in part current events and politics in pre-World War I Canada; correspondence with wife Katherine while serving in France 1918-1919; papers relating to his official responsibilities with the Michigan National Guard, as Judge Advocate, and as member of veterans organizations; include files relating to the Copper Miners' Strike of 1913 and to the Flint Sit-Down strike; also diaries, 1916-1919, of his experiences serving on the Mexican border and in France during the First World War; papers relating to Republican party activities in 1920 and 1924; and photographs.
86603; Aa 2; UAm
3 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This collection was donated by Mr. Winston Wessels (donor no. 4005 ) in July 1993.
The collection is open for research.
Samuel DeWitt Pepper was born on December 27, 1877 at Middlesex, Ontario, Canada. One of ten children, he grew up in Forest, Ontario, and received his early education at local schools. He was in the first graduating class at London Normal School in 1900, and also took private instruction in advanced academic subjects during the 1890s.
He was married to Katherine M. MacDonald in 1907, and they had two children - Elizabeth Marion (b. 1910) and Robert Hatfield (b. 1918).
He moved to Port Huron, Michigan in 1903, and studied law while working at the law office of Burt D. Cady; he also took courses at the University of Michigan Law Department during the summer of 1905. Pepper passed the Michigan State Bar in 1906 and practiced law in Port Huron until his appointment as Assistant Attorney General in Lansing in 1912.
Samuel Pepper's military career progressed concurrently with his work in law. He enlisted in the Michigan National Guard (MNG) in April 1905 and by September 1908 he achieved the rank of Second Lieutenant. In 1912, as part of an investigation into MNG members' behavior during a prison riot, Pepper was appointed Judge Advocate General of the MNG. This was the first of many times that he was to deal with the legal ramifications of civilian/military confrontations.
Following a copper strike in northern Michigan, in which the MNG was used to avert violence between company owners and strikers, Pepper wrote Michigan National Guard When Used in Aid of Civil Authorities; this was printed and issued as a legal guide for MNG officers. Pepper also served on the Mexican border (1916-17) and saw active service in France during the First World War, where he received a Distinguished Service Medal. As Judge Advocate of the Fifth Army Corps, he presided over General Courts Martial for the Army of Occupation.
After his discharge, Pepper returned to work in the Michigan Attorney General's office. He wrote the Michigan Insurance Code and was appointed to the state's Public Utilities Commission by his friend, Governor Alex Groesbeck. When Groesbeck left office in 1928, Pepper returned to private law practice in Port Huron. He remained active in Republican Party politics and the MNG.
As Judge Advocate General of the Michigan National Guard, Pepper played a key advisory role to both MNG and state government officials when riots and labor unrest occurred in Michigan during the 1930s. Over the course of the Flint sit-down strike in 1937, he counselled caution and restraint in the deployment of National Guardsmen. After retiring from the MNG in December 1941, Pepper was appointed Chief Deputy State Director of the Selective Service System for the duration of World War II.
After the war, Pepper returned once again to his law practice, was City Attorney of Port Huron, and became General Counsel of Michigan Life Insurance Company; he also took active part in revising Michigan state military laws in the early 1950s. Samuel Pepper died in Port Huron in 1960.
The Samuel D. Pepper papers cover Pepper's military service and legal career, as well as his relationships with family and friends. The collection provides particularly strong documentation of the impact which Pepper's Michigan National Guard (MNG) service had on personal and professional aspects of his life. The papers are divided into four main series: Personal, Military Activities, Professional and Political Activities, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Canada.; Copper Miners' Strike, Mich., 1913-1914.; France.; General Motors Corporation Sit-Down Strike, 1936-1937.; Mexico--Foreign relations--United States.; Michigan. National Guard.; Military art and science.; Pepper, Samuel Dewitt, 1877-1960.; Republican Party (Mich.); Strikes and lockouts--Michigan.; United States. Army--Military life.; United States--Foreign relations--Mexico.; Veterans--Michigan.; World War, 1914-1918.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Airplanes.; Aeronautics.; Calumet (Mich.); Camp Grayling (Mich.); Cannons.; Clothing and dress.; Copper Miners' Strike, Mich., 1913-1914.; Michigan. National Guard.; Military camps.; Pepper, Samuel Dewitt, 1877-1960.; Storms.; Strikes.; Women.
Genre/Form:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Personal
  The Personal series spans the dates 1893-1952. It includes a short unpublished biography of Pepper by collection donor Winston Wessels, written in 1963, which details his legal and military careers, as well as two autobiographical letters by Pepper, written in 1920 and 1952. The bulk of this series is made up of correspondence with family and friends in the United States and Canada. The letters provide a glimpse into relations between members of Pepper's extended family and details of daily life in pre-World War I Canada. These include discussions of current events and politics, particularly between 1900 and 1920. Letters from A.M. Dallas and Miles Pepper provide first-hand accounts of life in western Canada during the "boom" early in the century. The Pepper family genealogy by M.G. Reddon may be of use in determining family relationships.
  Samuel Pepper and his wife Katherine wrote to each other almost daily while he was serving in France (1918-1919) and this correspondence tells a great deal about the war as each of them experienced it. Other letters which describe war experiences are Robert Pepper's letters home from the Pacific in World War II; Samuel Pepper's correspondence with "war buddy" John LeFevre; and letters from a French acquaintance, Margaret Philbert. The latter contain vivid descriptions of life in France immediately following the Second World War. The A-Z folder contains letters to Pepper from Attorney General Grant Fellows and Alex Groesbeck written to Pepper while he was at the front in World War I.
  - Biographical sketch by Winston Wessels (rev. ed. 1993); autobiographical letters 1920, 1952; and clippings about SDP (Box 1)
  - Essay and notebook circa 1893-1896 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1895-1952
    - 1895-1903 (Box 1)
    - A-Z 1911-1945 (Box 1)
    - A.M. Dallas 1903-1918 (Box 1)
    - Annie Pepper Ferguson (sister) 1904-1911 (Box 1)
    - John LeFevre 1919-1947 (Box 1)
    - Catherine Pepper (mother) 1903-1915 (Box 1)
    - Dougald Pepper (brother) 1900-1912 (Box 1)
    - Elizabeth Pepper (daughter) 1917-1918, circa 1928 (Box 1)
    - Katherine MacDonald Pepper (wife) 1913-1919, 11 folders (Box 1)
    - Mary Pepper (sister) 1903-1930 (Box 1)
    - Miles Pepper (brother) 1900-1911 (Box 1)
    - Ralph C. Pepper (brother) 1903-1925 (Box 1)
    - Robert Pepper (son) 1932, 1941-1943 (Box 1)
    - William Pepper (brother) 1910-1930 (Box 1)
    - Margaret Philbert 1919, 1947 (Box 1)
    - Sarah Pepper Reddon (sister) 1903-1911 (Box 1)
    - Belle Pepper Wilkinson (sister) 1896-1918, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Pepper family genealogy by M.G. Reddon 1982 (Box 1)
- Military Activities
  The Military Activities series covers Pepper's military career from 1908 to 1952. Pepper's MNG papers are arranged chronologically and include general administrative records as well as Pepper's accounts of his military service. There are local newspapers and investigation transcripts from the 1913 copper strike, and the 1912-14 Judge Advocate General folder also contains correspondence relating to the strike. A manuscript account of Armistice Day at the front and a journal which Pepper kept on his return trip from France describe his thoughts about the war, as well as his views on military discipline. He also kept daily diaries of his experiences during service on the Mexican border and in France.
  MNG files from the 1920s and 1930s contain memos and correspondence regarding plans for training camps, regulations, Camp Grayling Bulletins, and reports, essays, and speeches by Pepper. MNG records from 1935 and 1937 relate to riots in Flint and to the sit-down strike; these include essays by Pepper on military responses to civil unrest. The Veterans' Groups subseries covers fundraising, memorial events, and social activities during the 1920s and 1930s.
  - Michigan National Guard
    - General correspondence 1908-1912 (Box 2)
    - LeRoy Pearson correspondence 1912-1919 (Box 2)
    - 1913-1914
      - Calumet Copper strike (Box 2)
      - Copper strike investigation transcripts 1914 (Box 2)
    - 1912-1917
      - Judge Advocate General administrative records, 4 folders (Box 2)
      - " Diary of Border Duty-1916" (Box 2)
    - 1918-1919
      - War Preparedness Board (Box 2)
      - World War I service in France:
        - Argonne-Meuse operations and miscellaneous AEF records (Box 2)
        - " Diary of German-American War Service", 2 folders (Box 2)
        - Judge Advocate memos and court martial records, 2 folders (Box 2)
        - Journal-experiences in France (Box 2)
        - Manuscript account of Armistice Day November 11, 1918 (Box 2)
    - 1919-1922
      - Speeches (Box 2)
      - Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Administration and correspondence 1921-1927, 7 folders (Box 2)
    - Essay-"Federal Control of National Guard" 1927 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence coursework 1927-1928 (Box 2)
    - Administration and correspondence 1928-1932, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Administration and correspondence, includes draft "plan of cooperation between military and civil authorities" 1933 (Box 2)
    - Administration and correspondence, includes memos on civil/military relations 1934 (Box 2)
    - 1935
      - Administration and correspondence (includes memos re: riots in Flint) (Box 2)
      - "Regulations Concerning Aid of Civil Authorities" (Box 2)
    - 1936
      - Administration and correspondence (Box 2)
      - Clippings "Relative to the Death and Funeral Services of Major-General Guy M. Wilson" (Box 2)
    - 1937
      - Administration and correspondence, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Correspondence with M.N.G. members' creditors (Box 3)
      - Flint sit-down strike recommendations and responses (Box 3)
      - Military law amendments correspondence (Box 3)
      - "Military Forces of Michigan in Aid of Civil Authorities" (Box 3)
    - Administration and correspondence 1939 (Box 3)
    - 1940
      - Administration and correspondence; includes memo on handling riots (Box 3)
      - Retirement law (Box 3)
    - Administration and correspondence 1945 (Box 3)
    - Citizens' Committee on reorganization of the M.N.G. 1946 (Box 3)
    - Military Retirement Law amendments 1947 (Box 3)
    - Michigan Military Law Revisions, drafts and correspondence 1949-1951 (Box 3)
    - Michigan Military Law Revision 1951 (Box 3)
  - Selective Service System 1941-1947 (Box 3)
  - Veterans' Groups
    - American Legion, Charles A. Hammond Post No. 8 (Box 3)
    - Fifth Corps Society 1920-1921 (Box 3)
    - Military Order of Foreign Wars 1927-1932 (Box 3)
    - Selective Service System 1941-1947 (Box 3)
    - Thirty-second Division Veterans Association (Red Arrows)
      - Haan Memorial 1926-1932 (Box 3)
      - Memos, clippings, fundraising letters 1920s-1930s, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Reunions 1932-1934, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 32nd Division News 1941 (Box 3)
- Professional and Political Activities
  The Professional and Political Activities series spans the period 1910 to 1953. Pepper's law practice, government service and Republican Party work tended to overlap, and this is evident in the correspondence files, which are arranged alphabetically. Many letters are requests for Pepper's help in obtaining jobs with the state government. Representative samples have been retained from the Attorney General's office correspondence, as have letters and legal briefs from the Michigan Life Insurance Company. The Republican Party folders includes essays, speeches and correspondence by Pepper which outline his active participation in intra-party politics and strategic planning in the 1920 and 1924 elections.
  - Attorney General's Office correspondence (a 20% sampling, in alphabetical order) 1919-1923 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Life Insurance Co. sample cases 1948, 1953 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Life Insurance Co. sample legal briefs 1946-1952 (Box 3)
  - Port Huron Exchange Club (Box 3)
  - Professional/political correspondence
    - 1910-1914 (Box 3)
    - 1925-1948, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Republican Party correspondence 1919-1920, 1924-1925 (Box 3)
  - Republican Party 1920 Gubernatorial Primary (Box 3)
  - Republican Party 1924 election (Box 3)
- Photographs
  Photographs have been divided into two folders; family pictures cover the years between about 1900 and the 1930s, while the military photographs run from roughly 1913 with a view of Calumet during the copper mining strike to 1943. The collection includes military pictures from the Mexican border and from the front in France, as well as photographs of Camp Grayling, the MNG training camp.
  - Personal and family pictures (Box 3)
  - Michigan National Guard circa 1915-1944 (Box 3)
  - Portraits of military acquaintances (Box 3)